<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An exact and sound discovery of the chiefe mysteries of jesuiticall iniquity</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1619</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 50 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 64 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A04410</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 14529</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S113297</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99848533</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99848533</idno>
            <idno type="VID">13633</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A04410)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 13633)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1687:20)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An exact and sound discovery of the chiefe mysteries of jesuiticall iniquity</title>
                  <author>Bargrave, Isaac, 1586-1643.</author>
                  <author>Micanzio, Fulgenzio, attrib. auth.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[102] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>W. Jaggard for F. Paxton,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1619]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Translated by Isaac Bargrave.</note>
                  <note>Imprint and translator from STC.</note>
                  <note>"A translation of 'Instruttione a ̀prencipi .. si governano li padri giesuiti', Poschiavo, 1617, now attrib. to Fulgenzio Micanzio. Probably suppressed by order of Buckingham."--STC.</note>
                  <note>A1 (blank?) and A2 (title page) lacking.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Emmanuel College (University of Cambridge) Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:13633:53"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13633:53" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN EXACT and ſound Diſcouery of all the chiefe Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of Ieſuiticall Iniquity.
<hi>With the whole Body of their Statiſme, and Diuel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Policy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Compoſed and publiſhed in Itali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, by a moſt graue and learned Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt, and faithfully tranſlated by I. B. Gods vnworthy Miniſter.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Printed for Peter Paxton, and are to</hi> be ſold at the ſigne of the Crane in Pauls Church yard, 1619.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:13633:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13633:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>To the right Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable, GEORGE <hi>Marqueſſe Buckingham,</hi> Viſcount
<hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>illiers,</hi> Baron of Whaddon, Lord High Admiral of England; Iuſtice in Eyre of all his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſties Forreſts, Parkes, and Chaſes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d Trent, Maſter of the horſe to his Maieſty, and one of the Gentlemen of his Maieſties Bed-chamber, Knight of the moſt noble Order of the Garter, and one of his Maieſties moſt Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Priuy Counſell of England &amp; Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat I dare i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitate His Maieſtie, in dedicating a Booke vnto your Lordſhip (ſince ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer

<pb facs="tcp:13633:2"/>Subiectes had ſuch a King to imitate) I hope your goodneſſe will be as gracious to pardon my preſumption, as it is pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erfull to conquer all enuy. The quantity of this Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe, is according to his Maieſties happy praeſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; tis ſhort, and will (I hope) rather direct, then diſtract greater employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; nor will the quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty I truſt bee diſpleaſing, though differing from that of his Maieſties Booke. That containes Prayer &amp; heauenly Meditation; this a Diſcouery of Ieſuiticall
<pb facs="tcp:13633:2"/>policy, and helliſh Ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. As that cannot but enlighten your Deuotion towardes God, for which your Honors ſo royall te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony of the King; ſo this cannot but enlighten your zeale to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth, which is ſo generally acknowledged by the people. That a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong all other kingdoms, the Ieſuites fiſh eſpecially for this Iſland, no man doubteth: and I dare pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, that in this litle Bark which is ſteered by one of their owne Mariners, your Honour may plainly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couer
<pb facs="tcp:13633:3"/>all the maine baytes they lay for vs. In my for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reine ſeruice to his Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty, I haue found many ſuch Pylates, euen among themſelues our profeſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies; all which by your Honourable command &amp; encouragement, ſhall bee ready to con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uct vs in the way of truth againſt this prodigeous Armado of Ignatian Furies, let them ſaile where they will, wee will beate them with their owne Weapons. In the fighting of which good fight for the truth of Ieſus Chriſt, we ſhall all glorie
<pb facs="tcp:13633:3"/>to haue ſo deuout an en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courager as your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippe: but none ſhall be more ready to venture his little all in ſo good a cauſe then</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Lordſhips deuoted Beadſman,</hi> Iſaac Bargraue.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:13633:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13633:4"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His ſhort en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe, wil ſerue as the key, to let thee in to the whole treaſury of Ieſui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall villany. It was lent me by one of the most Learned, Graue, and Wiſeſt Papistes that breaths that Ayre. He will tell vs, that all diuiſion and distraction is not found
<pb facs="tcp:13633:5"/>in Amsterdam, or in our Church, ſince all other or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders are here againſt the Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuites, and the Ieſuites a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Pope. He (though a stranger) will inform our miſerably-ſeduced Country<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, what good Angels the Ieſuites are, whom they ſo much adore; and to what trusty ſhepheards they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit their ſouls: whoſe blind obedience and deuotion, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing made a ſacrifice to Ieſui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall ambition, and their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion an onely meanes to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray the cauſe of God, their King, and country, haue had their merite thus Crowned
<pb facs="tcp:13633:5"/>with an Italian Prouerbe: <hi>Achimanca vn aſino fac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cia metter la ſella adoſſo vn Catolico Ingleſe. He that wants an Aſſe, let him ſet the ſaddle vpon an En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh Catholike.</hi> Poore Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuite-ridden ſoules, whome we cannot but pitty, while Romanists thus deride the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. God ſo ſhine into their hearts by the light of his Spirit, that euen the pen of this Papist, may work in them their own ſoules conuerſion, and the confuſion of their Enemies. And that it may teach them to conſider, how monstrous the whole Body of Poperie
<pb facs="tcp:13633:6"/>must needs bee, when theſe cheefe heads thereof the Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuites, how euer outwardly ſhewing ſo ſtrict Diſcipline and Deuotion, yet are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly compoſed of nought but damned Matcheuiliſme and vnhallowed Ambition.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:13633:6"/>
            <head>AN Impartiall Diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery, of Ieſuiticall <hi>Policie.</hi>
            </head>
            <byline>¶ Written in Italian by a <hi>Papiſt, and faithfully</hi> Tranſlated, by I. B.</byline>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat the Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Order of the Ieſuits, was at the firſt plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the Vineyarde of
<pb facs="tcp:13633:7"/>Chriſt, as a Tree which ſhould produce an Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dote againſt the poyſon of Hereſie, and ſuch bloſſoms of Chriſtian and religious workes, as by the ſweet ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uor of them ſinners might be conſtraind to bid adieu to the corruption of ſinne, and to proſecute the ſweet ſmell of Repentance, wee need no clearer demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration, then the lawes &amp; orders on the which this plant was grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded, by the firſt Founder thereof,<note place="margin">This Exor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dium will make you know, that the Author was a papiſt.</note> Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<hi>Ignatius.</hi> And ſurely, ſo long as by thoſe firſt fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers that gaue it life it was
<pb facs="tcp:13633:7"/>cheriſhed with the dew of Charity, and cultiuated conformable to the inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the firſt planter; It brought forth two braun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches: the one of loue to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God, the other to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards their Neighbor. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch that it was a won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to conſider the plentie of fruites which it brought forth in the excellent edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of Children, the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of ſoules, and the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of the Catholique Faith. But the Diuell, who makes vſe of all good in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentions, but as a Whet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone, grewe as eager and
<pb facs="tcp:13633:8"/>cunning to deſtroy this worke and enterprize, as the other to promote it: &amp; tooke occaſion euen from the greatneſſe it ſelf of this religious order, and from that admirable progreſſe, which in ſmall time it had made, to peruert the firſt inſtitution of it, with an ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificiall ſubtilty, in ſted of thoſe two firſt branches of Charity, now vtterly dry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vp hee hath ingrafted two other: the one of ſelf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loue, and the other of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit: from which the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian <hi>Republique</hi> receyues ſuch damage, that haply a
<pb facs="tcp:13633:8"/>greater cannot bee imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, as I am now about to demonſtrate in this Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe. In the which, I proteſt before God, I haue no motion either of Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt or paſſion, but an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent zeale of the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique good; for the which I do aſſure my ſelfe I was borne, and that Princes knowing their Artifice, may preuent them by op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portune remedies.</p>
            <p>Now we are to know, that the Religious orders of theſe Fathers the Ieſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ites being enlarged, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially by the education of
<pb facs="tcp:13633:9"/>Children (of which there is neither Citty nor King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome but hath need) was euen from the beginning thereof (by verie manie) much deſired, and by di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers Princes ſo fauoured, that in few yeeres it diffu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed it ſelfe, as far as other orders had done in manie hundreds. This greatneſſe which almoſt alwayes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duceth into mens minds a change of Cuſtome, raiſed vp in the heires of Father <hi>Ignatius,</hi> ſuch a loue to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards their Societie, that eſteeming that more profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table vnto the Church of
<pb facs="tcp:13633:9"/>God, and more helpefull in the reformation of the world, then all other Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, they concluded a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong themſelues to ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour with all Art and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry to giue encreaſe to it, and in that to giue gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth to the cauſe of <hi>Chriſt</hi> the good of the Church, nay (to vſe their owne words) to the onely Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>And here I had need of the ſubtilty of <hi>Aristotle</hi> to diſcerne, and the Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence of
<hi>Cicero,</hi> to expres thoſe maruellous meanes;
<pb facs="tcp:13633:10"/>(A thing which for the nouelty of it to many ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth incredulous) by which theſe Fathers ſtill gaine encreaſe to their ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety. But it ſhall bee ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient for me to point out only ſome few things, lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing a large roome for o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mens iudgements, to raiſe vp a forme of what I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dea themſelues ſhall think fitteſt. Yet I ſhall not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to propound ſom few heads, with which I intend to ſerue the Reader for the ground of his diſcourſe.</p>
            <p>And firſt, theſe Fathers
<pb facs="tcp:13633:10"/>the Ieſuites, thoght it was not ſufficient to promote their ſociety to that pitch of greatneſſe to the which they aſpired, onely by tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, preaching, or admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtring the moſt holy Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments, with other like religious exerciſes; becauſe though from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning (as I ſaid) they were kindly imbraced by many people, yet in proceſſe of time they perceiued, that either for ill ſatisfaction, or ſome other occaſion, what euer it was; the affection of many grewe colde to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards them; and therfore
<pb facs="tcp:13633:11"/>doubting leſt their growth ſhould end with their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fancy, they inuented two other meanes to enlarge their greatneſſe.</p>
            <p>The firſt, was to worke in the minds of Princes, &amp; conſequently of as manic others as they could, a baſe opinion of all other Religious Societies, diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uering their imperfections and after a cunning man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, from others depreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, raiſing theyr owne greatneſſe; and by this meanes they impatronized themſelues of many Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſteries,
<pb facs="tcp:13633:11"/>Abbeyes, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther maine poſſeſſions, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priuing thoſe Religious perſons that firſt enioyed them, both of them, and of all that belonged to them.</p>
            <p>The ſecond means was, to thruſt themſelues into affayres of State, gayning intereſt with the greateſt part of Chriſtian Princes; and that with as ſubtle &amp; artificious a deuice, as euer yet the worlde brought forth: into which, as it is very hard to penetrate, ſo it is (almoſt) impoſſible, ſufficiently to explaine it.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:13633:12"/>There reſides continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally in <hi>Rome</hi> the <hi>Father Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall,</hi> to whom all the reſt render moſt exact obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence: and there is choyce made of ſome other Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, who from the Aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaunce they alwayes giue him, are called his Aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ants; and there is one (at leaſt) of euery nation, who from that Nation takes his name. Hence, one is ſtyled the Aſſiſtant of <hi>France;</hi> a ſeeond, of <hi>Spaine;</hi> a third, of <hi>Italy;</hi> a fourth, of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land;</hi> a fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t, of
<hi>Austria;</hi> &amp; ſo of all other Prouinces &amp; Kingdomes: euery one of
<pb facs="tcp:13633:12"/>which, hath it aſsigned to him as his particular office to informe the <hi>Father Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall</hi> of all accidents of State, which occur in that Prouince or Kingdome, of which he is Aſſiſtant. And this Office he perfourmes by the meanes of his Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpondents, who reſide in the Principall Cities of that Prouince orkingdom: who with all induſtry firſt informe themſelues of the State, the Quality, Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, Inclination, and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention of Princes, and by euery Currier aduertiſe the Aſſiſtants of ſuch acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents
<pb facs="tcp:13633:13"/>as are newly diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered. And theſe againe communicate all vnto the <hi>Father Generall,</hi> who mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in Councell with all his Aſſiſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, they make an Anatomy (as it were) of the whole worlde, confer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the intereſt and deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeigns of all chriſtian Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. Heere they conſult of al freſh intelligences recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued from their Correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents, and curiouſly exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mining them, and confer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring them togither, at laſt they conclude, to fauour the affaires of one Prince, &amp; to depreſſe the deſignes
<pb facs="tcp:13633:13"/>of another, as ſhalbe moſt requiſite for their intereſt and profit. And as thoſe who are ſtanders by at ſome game, more eaſily diſcerne the ſtroake, then thoſe that giue it: ſo theſe Ieſuits hauing in one view the intereſt of all princes; know very wel how to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue the condition of place and time, &amp; how to apply the true meanes of aduancing the affayres of that Prince, from whome they know they ſhal draw moſt water to their owne Mils.</p>
            <p>Howeuer, this is a thing
<pb facs="tcp:13633:14"/>ſimply euill, that religious men ſhould ſo much inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mingle with matters of State, it being their dutie rather to attend the ſauing of their owne and other mens ſoules, being for that end onely retired from the world, but by this meanes they are more entangled, then the very ſeculare per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons themſelues, &amp; for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny moſt pernitious conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences, we ſhall find this their courſe moſt wicked, and worthy of a ſpeedy &amp; potent remedy.</p>
            <p>For firſt, theſe Ieſuits
<pb facs="tcp:13633:14"/>are Confeſſors to the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt part of the Nobilitie, thoroughout all Romaine Catholike eſtates. Nay, &amp; the better to attend them, they will not admit poore men, or poore women to their Confeſſions, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther aime to be Confeſſors to the Princes themſelues. So that by this courſe, it is eaſie for them to penetrate euery deſigne, euery reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution, and inclination, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well of Princes, as of Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects; of all which they ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dainly informe the Father Generall, or his Aſſiſtantes in Rome. Now any man
<pb facs="tcp:13633:15"/>that hath the leſt meaſure of vnderſtanding, may ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily perceiue, what a preiu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice they bring to Princes by this deuice, when onely their owne intereſt ſtirres them vp to that, to which (as to their laſt end) they direct all their endeuour.</p>
            <p>Secondly, whereas ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crecy is a proper and vnſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable Accident, which ſo accompanieth the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation of a State, that without it, the ruine of a State muſt needes follow. Therefore all Princes are moſt rigorous againſt
<pb facs="tcp:13633:15"/>thoſe, who diſcouer theyr ſecrets, puniſhing them as the enemies both of them and their Countrey. And as on the other ſide, to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the deſignes of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Princes, makes a man more cautelous, and more able to diſcerne his owne eſtate: and therefore they vſe to ſpend no ſmall ſum of money, in the maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of Ambaſſadors &amp; Intelligencers; yet are of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes deceiued too in their relations. But the Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuites (that is) their Father Generall and his Aſſiſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, as well by the Confeſſions
<pb facs="tcp:13633:16"/>and Conſultations, which their Correſpondents doe make, reſiding in all chiefe Citties of the Chriſtian worlde, as by meanes of their other Adherents, of whom we ſhall Diſcourſe hereafter, are moſt ſincere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and punctually aduerti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of all determinations, that are concluded in the moſt ſecret Councelles: ſo that they better know (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt) all the power, poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſions, expences, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes of Princes, then the Princes themſelues, &amp; that without any other expenſe then the cariage of letters:
<pb facs="tcp:13633:16"/>the which notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in <hi>Rome</hi> alone (as the Maſters of the Poſts relate to vs) arriſeth to ſixty, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenty, eighty, and ofte to an hundered Crownes of Gold for one Currier. So that they knowing ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly the affairs of al Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, do not onely diminiſh their credit among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, but wound their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation both with other Princes, &amp; with their own ſubiects, depreſſing or ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uancing their State at their pleaſure: and that ſo much the eaſier, becauſe by the ſame way of Confeſſions
<pb facs="tcp:13633:17"/>and Conſultations, they enter into the very ſecrets of the peoples ſoules: kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing who ſtands well affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted to the Prince, &amp; who reſts diſtaſted: ſo that by theſe relations which they haue of State-affaires, they may eaſily ſowe diſcord a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong Princes, occaſion a thouſand iealouſies, &amp; by their inſight into the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects affection, raiſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motions and diſcord, brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging into contempte the very perſon of the Prince. Whence we muſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>clude that the intereſt of State doth not comport, that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb facs="tcp:13633:17"/>Prince ſhould confeſſe himſelfe; much leſſe, that he ſhold permit any of his Confidents, Friendes, Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretaries, Counſellors, or other his cheefe Miniſters, to confeſſe themſelues to perſons, that attend ſo di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently to ſpy outmatters of State and to ſerue them ſelues of this means, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinuate into the fauour of Princes; ſince there is this day no want of Religious perſons, men both for life and learning, to be regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded equally with the Ieſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ites, whome in this kinde they may employ, &amp; who
<pb facs="tcp:13633:18"/>attend nothing els but the gouernment of ſoules, and of their Monaſteries.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, which is a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter diſcouery then yet wee haue made, or ſhall make heereafter, ye are to know that there are found amon<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>geſt them foure ſorts of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuites. The firſt, conſiſtes of certaine ſecular people, of both ſexes, adioyned to their ſociety, who liue vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a certaine obedience, which themſelues call a Blinde Obedience; ſqua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring all their particular ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions by the Ieſuites coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell,
<pb facs="tcp:13633:18"/>reſigning themſelues moſt readily in all thinges to be commanded by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: and theſe for the moſt part are Gentlemen or Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlewomen, the wealthyeſt Widdowes, or the richeſt Cittizens, or Marchantes; from all whome, as from fructiferous plants, the Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuites gather euery yeare, a copious harueſt of gold &amp; ſiluer. Of this kinde, are thoſe women, who (in <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taly</hi>) call themſelues <hi>Chet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine,</hi> who are induced by the Ieſuites, to forſake the world, while in the meane time, they get their pearls,
<pb facs="tcp:13633:19"/>apparrell, ornaments, fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niture of houſes, and fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally, very great poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
            <p>The ſecond ſort is, of men alone; but thoſe as well Prieſts as Lay-men: yet ſuch as liue a ſeculare life, and ſuch as oft-times by the mediation of the Ieſuites, obtaine Penſions, Church-liuings, Abbeyes and other reuennews: but theſe make a vowe to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue a habite of the ſocie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, at the pleaſure of the Father Generall; and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they are called Ieſuits
<pb facs="tcp:13633:19"/>in <hi>Voto:</hi> and by the labors of theſe men, the Ieſuites wondrouſly auaile them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues in the fabricke of their Monarchy. For they maintaine in all kingdoms and Prouinces, in al courts of Princes, and Pallaces of great men, ſuch of theſe as ſhall ſerue them in a kind, which I ſhall declare vnto you in the ſeauenth point of this diſcourſe.</p>
            <p>The third ſort of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuits are thoſe who remain in Monaſteries; and theſe are either Prieſts, Clerkes, or Conuerts; who becauſe
<pb facs="tcp:13633:20"/>at the firſt they came not from that profeſſion; may at the pleaſure of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther General be depriued of it, although of themſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues they haue no power to leaue it. And theſe beeing ſuch as haue no Office of importance, for the moſt part doe ſimply obey in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing that their Superi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ors command.</p>
            <p>The fourth ſort is of Politicke Ieſuites, through whoſe handes paſſeth the whole gouernment of reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion; and theſe are they, who being tempted by the
<pb facs="tcp:13633:20"/>diuel, with the ſame temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation that Chriſt had in the Goſpell, <hi>Haec omnia ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bi dabo,</hi> haue accepted the bargaine; and therfore la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to reduce their ſocie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to an abſolute Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy, and to place the head thereof at <hi>Rome,</hi> where all the principal affairs of the Chriſtian world meete to gether. There reſides the head of theſe Politicians, (which is their Generall) with a great number of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of the ſame profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, who being firſt infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med from their Spies, of all ſuch waighty &amp; impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant
<pb facs="tcp:13633:21"/>buſineſſe, as are to be treated in the Court of <hi>Rome,</hi> hauing firſt among themſelues agreed of ſuch ends, as for their own inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt they deſire; each one takes his office to go eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry day their circuit throgh the Courts of Cardinals, Ambaſſadours, and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates: with whome (cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ningly) they inſinuat their diſcourſe of ſuch buſineſſe as is then in hand, or ſhort<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly to be handled, repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting it to them after what manner they pleaſe, and in the ſame ſhape, that by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flection from theyr owne
<pb facs="tcp:13633:21"/>ends, themſelues doe ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend it; ofttimes chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging the aſpect of the bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſines, and ſhewing blacke for white. And becauſe the firſt interpretations, made eſpecially by religious me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, are wont to make a nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble impreſſion in themind of him that heares them: hence it proceedes, that many times, moſt impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant buſineſſe treated by the Ambaſſadors of Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and other graue per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of the Roman court, haue not atained that ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe which Princes expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, becauſe the Ieſuites
<pb facs="tcp:13633:22"/>had praeoccupated theyr minds with theyr oblique relations, effecting that thoſe Ambaſſadors, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Agents, ſhould haue but ſmal credit with them.</p>
            <p>And the ſame artifice that they vſe with the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates of <hi>Rome,</hi> they vſe alſo with other Princes, either by themſelues, or by the meanes of their Penſiona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Ieſuites out of <hi>Rome;</hi> ſo that wee may conclude, that the greaterpart of bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſe thoroughout the Chriſtian World, dooth paſſe through the Ieſuites
<pb facs="tcp:13633:22"/>handes; and thoſe onely take effect, againſt which they make no oppoſition. Moſt ſtupendious and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penetrable is the Art that in this kind they vſe, which though it cannot by mee be perfectly deſcribed, yet may it liuely bee deſcryed by any Prince, who will but daigne to read this lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle touch y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I giue of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; becauſe hee will preſently reflect vpon what thinges haue paſt: and as he ſhall vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d the truth of my diſcourſe, calling to mind with what art things haue beene handled, he will diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couer
<pb facs="tcp:13633:23"/>more of that, which will ſeeme ſtrange &amp; mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uellous vnto him. For not beeing content with this their cloſe Artifice, by which they thruſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelus into the affayres of the World, with perſwaſion that it is the onely meanes to archieue that Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chall Iuriſdiction at which they aime; they made ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication to Pope <hi>Gregory</hi> the thirteenth, That for the time to come, he wold publiquely fauour theyr proiect: and repreſenting it to him vnder the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique good of the church,
<pb facs="tcp:13633:23"/>they required that hee would commaund all his Legates, and Apoſtolical Nuncios, to take to them euery one for his compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion and confident, ſome Ieſuite, by whoſe counſell he ſhould be gouerned in all his actions.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, by theſe cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning carriages, and their inſight into State buſines, the cheefe Ieſuites haue gotten the loue of manie Princes, as well Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall as Spirituall; which Princes they do perſwade, that they haue ſaide and
<pb facs="tcp:13633:24"/>done many things for their good; and hereupon haue followed two waighty in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conueniences. Firſt, that abuſing the friendſhip and goodneſſe of thoſe Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, they haue not cared to diſtaſte many priuate, but otherwiſe rich &amp; No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Families, vſurping the wealth of widdowes, and leauing their family in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treame miſery: alluring to their Religion, and to fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent their Schooles, the moſt noble ſpirits; who if haply they ſhall fall out to bee vnable and vnfitte for their purpoſe, vnder ſome
<pb facs="tcp:13633:24"/>honeſt pretext, they li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe them from their ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety; but withall lay hold of their eſtates, of which their ſociety will needs be inueſted heyres. In the mean time abſolutely ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluding the poore from their ſchooles, directly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the orders of the fore-named Father <hi>Igna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius,</hi> and the intention of thoſe their Patrons, who gaue them their poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, not that they ſhould ſerue their owne commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity, but the Chriſtian Commonwealth.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:13633:25"/>The ſecond inconueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence is, that theſe Ieſuites cunningly make the world knowe the friendſhip and inwardneſſe they retayne with Princes, ſetting it forth a litle more then in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede it is, to the end that they may gaine the loue of their Miniſters, and ſo procure, that all men ſhal recur to them for fauors; thus they publiquely vant, that they can make Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals, Nuncios, Lieutena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, Gouernors, and other of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers; nay ſome of them haue plainly affirmed, that their Generall could doe
<pb facs="tcp:13633:25"/>more then the Pope him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe; and others haue ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, that it is better to bee of that order which makes Cardinalles, then to bee a Cardinal. And theſe thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges they divulge ſo pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likely, that there is not any man who familiarly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſeth with them, to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they relate not theſe, or ſuch like things.</p>
            <p>Fiftly, hauing laide the ground-work of this their practicke in State, they pretend a power to raiſe or ruine whomſoere they pleaſe, and indeede ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
<pb facs="tcp:13633:26"/>vſe of religion onely for a cloake, whereby they may gaine credite, they make times attaine theyr ends. But when they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound any man vnto the Prince for preferment, they neuer make choiſe of him who is moſt fit &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruing; but rather op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to ſuch an one, when they know he is not parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all on their ſide: and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes aduance ſuch per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons as make for their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt, without any regard whether he be well affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the Prince, whether meritorious or fit to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergo
<pb facs="tcp:13633:26"/>that office to which he is nominated: whence there oft ariſeth diſturba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to the Prince, ſolleuations and diſguſts amongſt the people.</p>
            <p>Sixtly, as the Maſter of a Gally, when hee per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiues a good gale fayre for his voyage; but vvith once whiſtling makes all the gally-ſlaues fal to their Oares, and ſtretch them before the veſſel: ſo when in the Dyets, &amp; aſſemblies (which theſe Fathers con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually make by their Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall and his Aſſiſtants in
<pb facs="tcp:13633:27"/>
               <hi>Rome</hi>) they conclude it fit for their turne, that ſome one perſon ſhould be pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>moted to dignity; the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Generall ſignifyes ſo much to thoſe that reſide elſewhere; and all thoſe with one conſent, at an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant ioyne all their forces to make him attayne that honor which they intend him: and he ſhould be ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry vngrateful, if afterwards in all occurrents, he ſhold not ſerue the Ieſuites with the like zeal that they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred him. And becauſe ſuch a man, nay many ſuch men (for many dependa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts
<pb facs="tcp:13633:27"/>in this kinde the Ieſuites haue) holde themſelues more obliged to the Ieſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ites, then to their Prince, of whom they haue recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued their honour &amp; great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, therefore they ſerue the Ieſuites with a greater affection then the Prince himſelf. Thus they delude their Princes, who imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning they haue gotten a truſty ſeruant, haue onely made way for a Spy of the Ieſuites; of whom they of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes ſerue themſelues tot he dammage of that Prince, who aduanced him. I could with mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt
<pb facs="tcp:13633:28"/>examples confirm this my Diſcourſe, if daily ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience &amp; common fame were not a ſufficient con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation to it. But not to make my ſelf ouer-tedious I will paſſe to ſome other thinges, concluding that this happily is the cauſe, why the Ieſuites are wont to call their Religion, <hi>A Grand-Monarchy;</hi> as if they gouerned all Princes and their miniſters at their pleaſure. And it is not lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g ſince, that one of the chief of them, beeing publikely to treat with an illuſtrious Prince, in the name of the
<pb facs="tcp:13633:28"/>Society, he beganne with theſe wordes full of arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gancie, and grounded vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a conceit of their Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy; <hi>Our Society hath alwayes maintained good in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligence with your Grace, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Seuenthly, theſe Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers take great paines, to let the World know, that all thoſe who are any way in eſtimation with theyr Prince, haue beene theyr fauourites, and borne vp by their hands; ſo that by this meanes they are more Patrons of the Subiectes
<pb facs="tcp:13633:29"/>affections, then the prince himſelfe. And this is a no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table preiudice vnto the Prince; aſwell becauſe no reaſon of State doth com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port, that religious per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons ſo ambitious and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liticke, ſhould bee ſo farre Patrons of the will of the Miniſters, that whenſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer they pleaſe, they can cauſe treaſon and ſolleua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: As alſo that by this meanes, that is by the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diation of the Miniſters their adherents, they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce into the Princes ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice either for Counſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers or Secretaries, ſome
<pb facs="tcp:13633:29"/>of thoſe Ieſuites in <hi>Voto,</hi> of whom I diſcourſed before And theſe againe procure the Prince to entertayne ſome Ieſuite for his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſor or Preacher. And thus all theſe together, do ſerue as Intelligencers to the Father Generall; to whom they render an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act account of all that paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth in the moſt ſecret Councels. Whence it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedes, that manie times we ſee deſigns preuented, and ſecrets of the greateſt importance diſcouered; yet no man can ſearch out the true Author, but ofte
<pb facs="tcp:13633:30"/>thoſe are moſt ſuſpected, who are leaſt in fault.</p>
            <p>Eightly, as by Nature ſubiects are woont to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the inclination of their Prince; ſo all thoſe that giue obedience to their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Generall, perceiuing that he cheefely attends to matter of State, &amp; by that meanes endeuours to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proue and enrich their ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety, they alſo apply the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues that way; &amp; making vſe of their Kindred and Friends, aſſoile to pene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trate the very heartes of Princes, and their moſt ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret
<pb facs="tcp:13633:30"/>deſignes, only to giue notice of them, eyther to the Aſſiſtants at
<hi>Rome,</hi> or to the Father Generall: by this meanes to procure themſelues their fauour, &amp; attain ſome dignity, which by any other meanes they could neuer haue reacht. For amongſt them, none are euer preferred to anie Office of importance, but onely thoſe whome they know prone to aduaunce their ſociety to that height of greatnes to which they aſpire, and conſequently none but ſuch as are kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen to be ſufficient in the
<pb facs="tcp:13633:31"/>managing of State-buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
            <p>Ninthly, as from diuers Flowers and Hearbes, by meanes of a Lymbecke, a man may drawe ſuch an Oyntment, as is fit to heal a mortall wound; and as from ſeuerall bloſſomes, Bees ſucke Hony: ſo theſe Ieſuites, from the infallible relation which they haue of all Princes affayres, and of all accidents that occur in euery State, by the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of their diſcourſe, they extract from them theyr
<pb facs="tcp:13633:31"/>owne commoditie, which is the only remedy to cure that their inuincible wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of Couetouſueſſe and am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition; and they compoſe a certaine Art of their own profit, by which they ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne their owne ends, as well from other mens good, as ill; but more of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten from their il, then from their good.</p>
            <p>Thus they are wont to ſhackle with their Fetters, that Prince into whoſe ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets they haue ſpied, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounding to him that they haue the onely excellent
<pb facs="tcp:13633:32"/>meanes to make him the Maſter of his deſires: but when by this meanes they haue drawne theyr owne purpoſes from him, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering that the too ſwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling greatneſſe of that Prince may one day proue preiudiciall vnto them, as Aduocates doe their cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, they prolong as much as they can the ſucceſſe of that buſineſſe; and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards with ſtrange dexte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and wondrous iug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, they vtterly ruine thoſe deſignes to vvhich they had giuen a begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:13633:32"/>The league of <hi>Fraunce</hi> treated and concluded by them, not long after they abandoned, when they ſaw things proſper on the Kings ſide: and England, ſo often promiſed by them to the Spaniardes, yet in ſuch manner perfourmed, ſo confirmes this my Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, that there needs no farther proofe.</p>
            <p>Tenthly, from what hath beene already ſayde, it neceſſarily followes, that
<pb facs="tcp:13633:33"/>the Ieſuites haue no good intention towardes anie Prince what euer, eyther temporall or ſpirituall; but onely ſerue them ſo farre, as they may ſerue theyr owne commodity.</p>
            <p>Nay, it followeth yet further, that no Prince, much leſſe any vnder Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates, can make the like vſe of them, becauſe they ſhew themſelues at the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie ſame time, equally af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected to all; making them ſelues French with French men, Spaniards with Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niardes, and ſo with all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb facs="tcp:13633:33"/>according as the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion requires; fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which, they do intend to extract their profite. They haue no regard of the preiudice of one more then of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and therefore thoſe enterprizes in which they haue intermedled, haue ſeldome times ſucceeded well, beecauſe they haue no purpoſe to ſerue fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then their owne inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt dictates to them. And in this, the Artifice which they vſe, is moſt notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous; ſome of them fain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing themſelues to be parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all
<pb facs="tcp:13633:34"/>to the crown of <hi>France,</hi> others to <hi>Spaine,</hi> others to the Emperour, and ſome to other Princes, of whom they deſire to bee fauou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.</p>
            <p>And if any of theſe Princes pleaſe to make vſe of ſome Ieſuite, whom he holdes for his confident friend, hee immediately writes to the Father Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, the buſineſſe which hee hath to treate, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pects his anſwere, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with order what hee ſhall doe, and conforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to that Commiſſion he
<pb facs="tcp:13633:34"/>rules himſelfe; neuer re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garding whether that Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der be conformable to the intention of the Prince, who commits the care of that buſineſſe to him: but if the ſociety be ſerued, he takes little care, what ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice hee doeth vnto the Prince.</p>
            <p>Beſides this, becauſe the Ieſuites vnderſtande the intereſt of all Princes, and are moſt knowing in all thinges daylie treated in ſecret Counſelles, thoſe
<pb facs="tcp:13633:35"/>who pretend to hold with France, propound to the King, and his principall Miniſters, certaine condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of State, and impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant conſiderations, which are ſent to them from their Politicke Fathers at <hi>Rome.</hi> And thoſe that pretend to hold with the Crowne of Spaine, doe iuſt the ſame with them, and ſo with the reſt. From which courſe of theirs, there ariſeth ſuch a diffidence in the hearts of Chriſtian Princes, that none giue credit to other; which is a maine preiudice
<pb facs="tcp:13633:35"/>to the publike peace, and vniuerſall welfare of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendome: the which diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of theirs, is that which makes it ſo difficult a thing, to conclude a lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue againſt the common enemy, &amp; precious peace to be of ſo little valewe a mongſt Princes.</p>
            <p>Furthermore, vvith theſe artificious deuices, they haue ſo opened the eyes of the world, and ſo ſharpened mens wittes in matter of State, that this day, to the notable preiu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice of the holye Church,
<pb facs="tcp:13633:36"/>they attend to nothing els but matter of policie, and poyſe all their actions in that ballance.</p>
            <p>But to the end, that theſe Ieſuiticall ſtratagems may yet appeare more plainly, I cannot here conceale the meanes, by which they in ueigle Princes to their par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. There are ſome yeares nowe paſt, ſince one of theſe Fathers, called father <hi>Parſons,</hi> the Aſſiſtant of England, wrote a booke a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the ſucceſſion of the
<pb facs="tcp:13633:36"/>King of Scotland, to the Crowne of England: And another Father, called
<hi>Crittonius,</hi> with ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of the ſame order, in a Book which they wrote, defended the Title of the King of Scotland; oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the opinion of Father <hi>Parſons,</hi> and faining to be at diſcord amongſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues: although all this was (indeede) cunningly done, and by the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of their Father Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall, onely for this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, that whoſoeuer ſhold ſucceede in the Kingdome
<pb facs="tcp:13633:37"/>of England, they might haue an excellent Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to worke in him a great good opinion of their Society, and to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract their own ends from him.</p>
            <p>A faire example to ſhew vs, that Princes are the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects of all Ieſuiticall acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and determinations: and (by conſequence) to make good their own ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>That their Societie is a Grand Monarchy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Againe, that the trueth
<pb facs="tcp:13633:37"/>of this may appeare, that the Ieſuites haue no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard, whether they pleaſe or diſpleaſe any Prince, where it toucheth vppon their owne commoditie; although the experience of infinite things paſt ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth it as cleare as the Sun it ſelfe; yet the particular which I ſhal here ſubioyn, will render it euerie way moſt euident.</p>
            <p>There is no perſon in the Worlde, whom they are more bounde to ſerue
<pb facs="tcp:13633:38"/>and obey then the By<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoppe of Rome; not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for many other reaſons, but eſpecialy becauſe they make a particular vowe to obey him. Yet when <hi>Pius Quintus</hi> went about to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme ſome of theſe Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, reducing them vnto the performance of theyr dutie in the Quire, they would not obey him; e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteeming that a notorious preiudice to their ſociety: and thoſe fewe of them, who yeelded themſelues to the Popes pleaſure, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepting that profeſſion;
<pb facs="tcp:13633:38"/>were alwayes afterwardes in mockery called by their fellowes, <hi>Quintini:</hi> nor could euer any of them get the leaſt preferment a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them.</p>
            <p>In the ſame kinde, they oppoſed glorious Saint <hi>Charles,</hi> Arch-byſhoppe of
<hi>Millain,</hi> who as Legate <hi>alatere</hi> to his Holyneſſe, endeauoured to reduce them to a Religious Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline.</p>
            <p>But what ſhould I ſpeake of theſe, ſince they obey not the Sacred Cannons them-ſelues, but agaynſt
<pb facs="tcp:13633:39"/>their Decrees, make Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandize of Pearles, Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bies, and Diamondes, the which they bring from the <hi>Indies;</hi> and there is an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion, that the greateſt part of precious Stones, which are ſolde in <hi>Venice,</hi> belong to the Ieſuits. The ground of which opinion, hath beene receiued from their owne brokers, whom they haue emploied in the ſale of them.</p>
            <p>But that they are no faithfull ſeruants vnto the Byſhoppe of Rome, thoſe Fathers knowe well; who
<pb facs="tcp:13633:39"/>for defaulte of theyr ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, were called by pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe to Rome. I neyther will, nor can name them, nor will I wade farther in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this matter, as wel that I may not bee compelled to ſpeake of ſome Prince, whom my Diſcourſe will not very well pleaſe, (my ſelfe deſiring to do ſeruice to all, and to offend none) as beecauſe I intend not here to make an inuectiue againſt the Ieſuites; but onely to giue a ſhorte and plaine draught of theyr courſes and cuſtomes.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:13633:40"/>For, as many times we behold one afflicted with ſome greeuous infirmitie, ſending forth ſuch lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table cryes, as reach hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen it ſelfe; and euery one perceyues that the man is terribly indiſpoſed, but no man is able to diſcerne the originall cauſe of his euill: ſo the whole worlde com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaines of the Ieſuites; ſome for beeing perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, others for being trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherouſly ſerued by them: but the miſchiefe ſtill re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines
<pb facs="tcp:13633:40"/>among vs. Nor is the cauſe therof eaſily diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couered; which is nothing elſe but a prodigeous and immenſe deſire, which they haue to encreaſe their owne power: in reſpect whereof, they eſteeme in nothing to diſtaſt any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to deceiue Princes, to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe the poore, to extort from Widdowes their e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates, to ruinate moſt no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Kingdomes, nay many times, by their interming<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling with alimportant bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſe, to cauſe iealouſies and deſpight among Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian
<pb facs="tcp:13633:41"/>Princes.</p>
            <p>Now, as there woulde follow a great inconueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, if that part which were laſt formed by Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, as an inſtrument to ſerue the reſt that are more noble; ſhould attract vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it ſelfe all the pureſt blood and vitall ſpirites, becauſe this were the way vtterly to diſſolue the whole: So it is as incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenient, that the religion of the Ieſuites, planted in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the bodye of the holye Church, as an inſtrument for the conuerſion of He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retickes,
<pb facs="tcp:13633:41"/>and the reduction of ſinners to Repentance, ſhould bring within theyr owne power, all the moſt waighty and important affayres of Princes &amp; Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates, and extracting from them the verie life and ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of their intereſt, ſhould conuert them vnto their owne commoditie. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe from hence both pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate and publike peace is diſturbed, manie depreſt which were worthy to bee exalted, and many exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted which were worthy to bee depreſt, with a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand
<pb facs="tcp:13633:42"/>other inconuenien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, that would follow vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it.</p>
            <p>I could adduce many Reaſons, taken from ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience it ſelfe, to demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate what an ingordgious ambition the Ieſuites haue to encreaſe their greatnes: but it ſhall heere ſuffice to make it knowne from Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Parſons</hi> owne words, recorded in a Booke of his compoſed in the Engliſh tongue, and intituled, <hi>The Reformation of England.</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:13633:42"/>Where hauing firſt bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Cardinall <hi>Poole,</hi> and hauing alſo obſerued ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny wantes and imperfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in the Councell of <hi>Trent;</hi> at length hee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes, That when Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land ſhould returne to the Romiſh Catholike Fayth, he would reduce it to the forme and ſtate of the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitiue Church, making common all Eccleſiaſtical goodes, and aſſigning the charge of them vnto ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen <hi>Sauij</hi> or Wiſe men, which ſhould bee Ieſuites, and who ſhould make di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtribution
<pb facs="tcp:13633:43"/>of goods at their pleaſure. Nor is it his will, nay he forbiddes it vnder a greeuous penaltie, that any religious perſon, of what order ſoeuer, ſhould return into England with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out their Licenſe, reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing that none ſhould en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter there, but thoſe who ſhould bee maintained by Almes.</p>
            <p>But as it ofte falls out, that ſelfeloue ſo blinds the wiſeſt man, that hee bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſeſt; it is
<pb facs="tcp:13633:43"/>moſt ridiculous which the ſame Father ſubioynes in that place. When Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land (ſayth hee) ſhal once bee reduced to the true Faith, it will not bee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenient, that the Pope (at the leaſt for fiue yeares ſpace) ſhould looke to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue any fruite from the Eccleſiaſticall Benefices of this Kingdome; but remit all into the hands of thoſe ſeuen
<hi>Sauij,</hi> who ſhoulde diſpenſe them, as they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued beſt, for the good of the Church. This being his deſigne, that the firſt
<pb facs="tcp:13633:44"/>fiue yeares being paſt, by ſome other inuention (of which they are verie full) they woulde re-confirme the ſame priuiledge for fiue yeares more, and ſo onward, till they had vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly excluded his Holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe from England. Now who ſeeth not heere (as in a Table) the Couetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and the Ambition of the Ieſuites, naturally de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed; together with the deſire they haue, to make themſelues Monarches? And who ſeeth not, with what cunning they endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uor
<pb facs="tcp:13633:44"/>to promote their own intereſt, procuring it ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from others good, or ill? What ſhould I ſay more of them? In the time of <hi>Gregory</hi> the thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth, did they not make it their requeſt, that they might bee inueſted of all the Pariſh Churches in <hi>Rome?</hi> That they might there lay a foundation of their Monarchy? And that which they could not get in
<hi>Rome,</hi> haue they not finally obtained in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land; where not long ſince they haue choſen an Arch
<pb facs="tcp:13633:45"/>prieſt, one of the Ieſuites in <hi>Voto;</hi> who in ſted of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tecting the Clergy, like a rauening Wolfe perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutes all ſuch Prieſtes, as are not dependent vppon the leſuites, driuing them to termes of deſperation, and depriuing them (vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a great penaltie) of mutuall communication: ſo that by this time almoſt all the Engliſh Romiſh Clergy are Ieſuites in <hi>Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to,</hi> nor do they accept any into their Colledges, who hath not paſt his worde to become a Ieſuite: ſo that
<pb facs="tcp:13633:45"/>when that kingdome ſhall returne to the Auncient Faith, England will bee like to giue a beginning to an abſolute Ieſuiticall Monarchy, becauſe al the Eccleſiaſtical reuennews, all the Abbeyes, Benefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, Biſhopprickes, Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prieſtſhips &amp; other digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties ſhall be conferred on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by the Ieſuites.</p>
            <p>I here let paſſe manie things as the pretentions, which they make concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning other mens eſtates,
<pb facs="tcp:13633:46"/>howe iealous they are of their welfare, and deſirous of their proſperitie: as the fauour which they endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour to gaine from Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, by making them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue, that their ſubiectes are moſt deuote to theyr religion, and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that they are able to make them well affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the perſon of theyr Prince. Such euident thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges as theſe, I leaue for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery one to obſerue; and with four brief conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions I will conclude this preſent Diſcourſe.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:13633:46"/>Firſt, that men of ſuch high ſpirit, and ſuch rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching deſignes, are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes louers of noueltie, euer ſearching for it, and begetting it; becauſe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſome new raiſed mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, it is impoſſible they ſhould attaine their ends. And therefore, the Ieſuits cannot be helpfull to anie Prince, that eyther loues peace, or the conſeruati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his own eſtate, ſince they are more likely to be the cauſe of much trouble and commotion; nay hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to put in compromize
<pb facs="tcp:13633:47"/>his whole ſtate, if he fauor not their party, or bee not partially gouernd by their counſell.</p>
            <p>Secondly, if theſe who haue not temporall iuriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, are able to cauſe ſuch great, and ſo prodigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous diſturbance in the World, what thinke you would they doe, if one of them ſhould by chance be created Pope? Firſt, hee would ſtuffe the Conſiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry with Ieſuites, &amp; by that meanes perpetuate the
<pb facs="tcp:13633:47"/>Popedome to them: and then directing themſelues by their inſight, and intereſt of State, and hauing the Arme and power of the Pope, they would be enabled to put in danger the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate of many Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, eſpeciallie of thoſe who are neigh bors and confiners.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, it would
<pb facs="tcp:13633:48"/>be the deſign of that Pope (if he could by any meanes) to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſt their order of ſome Citty, or tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall Iuriſdiction, with the which they would afterwardes make way for a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand other deſignes, whichthey could ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer effect without the damage of other Princes.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:13633:48"/>Fourthly, when the Conſiſtorie ſhoulde be entirely Ieſuited, the whole patrimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of Chriſt wold be in their hands; and as one that hath the dropſie, the more he drinkes, the more he thirſts; ſo their Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition growing with their greatnes, wold occaſion a world of trouble. Now, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ther is nothing
<pb facs="tcp:13633:49"/>more ſubiect vnto change then matter of State, theſe fathers with all their power and cunning, would endeuour to alter the courſe of affairs, that they might finally in duce the forme and proiect of their own gouernment, and by that means abſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly immonarchize the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues. They haue had it long in their heads
<pb facs="tcp:13633:49"/>to gaine into theyr ſociety the ſonne of ſome Prince, vvho ſhould abſolutely in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſt the companie of his ſtate; and this they had long ſince attained, if ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers wiſely ſpying out their deſign, had not preuented them. But hadde they once obtained that, they would without anie difficulty, haue made
<pb facs="tcp:13633:50"/>themſelues Patrones of the ſtate Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall; and as they are very inuentiue &amp; ſubtle, they woulde afterward haue foud out a thouſand waies howe to enlarge it. Thus they wold haue wanted no meanes, that might make the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> maſters of their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects: and if nothing els would haue done it, the ielouſies which
<pb facs="tcp:13633:50"/>they would haue rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in the mindes of their confining prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, would haue don the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> no ſmall ſeruice.</p>
            <p>It is therefore moſt neceſſary, that for the preſeruation of publike peace, &amp; for the maintainance of ſtates, for the increaſe of the holye Church, and for the common good of the vvhole
<pb facs="tcp:13633:51" rendition="simple:additions"/>world, that <hi>Paul</hi> the fifts Holineſſe, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with other Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, ſhold ſet bounds and limits to this ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety, whoſe deſires are ſo extremely in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinate, leaſt haply that followe, which was anciently effect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the <hi>Dauidi,</hi> (whoſe courſes the Ieſuites ſeem to imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate) who were not deſtroyd, til the time
<pb facs="tcp:13633:51" rendition="simple:additions"/>of <hi>Claudius</hi> the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror.</p>
            <p>And when I ſhall bee commaunded to write my opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cerning an oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune remedy howe to rectifie theſe fathers without anie hurt to them, but indeede to their great good (de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring rather to make them Monarches of ſoules, which are the
<pb facs="tcp:13633:52" rendition="simple:additions"/>treaſurie of Chriſt, then of the world, or of the profite of the world, which is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe but vile dung) J am readie to perform it with cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, and with all that ability, which it ſhal pleaſe God to beſtow vpon me.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Laus Deo.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:13633:52"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13633:54"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:13633:54"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:13633:55"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:13633:55"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:13633:56"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:13633:56"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:13633:57"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:13633:57"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:13633:58"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:13633:58"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:13633:59"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:13633:59"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:13633:60"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:13633:60"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:13633:61"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:13633:61"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:13633:62"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:13633:62"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:13633:63"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:13633:63"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:13633:64"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:13633:64"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
